<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Projects | Gaurav Agarwal</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/</link><atom:link href="https://gauravag99.github.io/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Projects</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://gauravag99.github.io/media/icon_hu3cc14bcc07eb590526d6c6755cf97d5f_13271_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Projects</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/</link></image><item><title>Two stage double frequency up-conversion scheme</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/superhet/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/superhet/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Superconducting qubits have emerged as one of the front-runners in the development of quantum processors and require amplitude and phase modulated microwave frequency pulses for control and measurement. A common method for generating these pulses is the single side band up-conversion scheme which utilizes an IQ Mixer and two modulating signals from arbitrary waveform generators. In this thesis, we discuss an alternative scheme, referred to as double frequency up-conversion, which aims to reduce the number of required modulating signals to one, eschews periodic calibrations and accommodates a wider range of qubit frequencies. We partially implement this scheme, demonstrate the measurement and analysis of a single qubit, and present evidence that the long-term stability of the alternative scheme is comparable to that of the standard setup.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Superconducting Tunnel Junctions</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/tunneljunc/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/tunneljunc/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>One of the pioneering methods of confirming the band gap predicted by the
BCS theory was using superconducting tunnel junctions. We outline the low temperature techniques used and measure electron tunneling in normal(Ag) - superconductor(NbN) tunnel junctions. We confirm the predictions of the BCS theory. We demonstrate phenomenological factors that are intricately linked to the physics of superconductors. Further, we measure these tunnel junctions in magnetic fields and present Maki analysis on the data collected. Python programs are
also developed for automatic data analysis and parameter extraction.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Graphene - Electronic Properties and Defects</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/graphene/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/graphene/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Graphene is one of the first 2-D materials to be discovered. We examine its
physical structure and review the tight-binding model of Graphene with the next-
nearest neighbour interaction. Only considering nearest neighbour hopping, we
demonstrate the importance of Dirac points, the onset of the relativistic for-
mulation and electrons acquiring pseudo-spin. We also show the e-h symmetry
breaking on the inclusion of next-nearest hopping. Additionally, we derive the
commonly stated density of states using Green’s function. Further, we model
substitutional impurities in the Graphene lattice by the Slater-Koster model and
derive the change in the band structure.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>fractional Brownian Motion (fBM)</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/fracbrown/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/fracbrown/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Brownian Motion serves as the foundation of a myriad of statistical modelling. Here, we discuss the statistical properties of Weiner processes, and introduce Brownian Motion as a continuous Weiner process. Further, we model it using Langevin and Fokker-Planck equations and study the motion of particles in a 1-D box. This is supplemented by simulations. Further, &lt;em>fractional Brownian Motion&lt;/em> is introduced as a generalisation and its statistical properties are studied. Its non-trivial simulation is also done by two methods.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Development of a Data Acquisition system</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/dataacq/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/dataacq/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Basket of experiments in the UG lab.</title><link>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/uglab/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://gauravag99.github.io/project/uglab/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>